Finding Aid for Students' Army Training Corps (University of Michigan) records, 1918-1919
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Students' Army Training Corps (University of Michigan) records 1918-1919
United States. Army. Students’ Army Training Corps (University of Michigan)
1.5 linear feet and 2 oversize volumes
87323 Bimu E27 2
United States Army program to train some of its members at participating universities and colleges (including the University of Michigan) in various technical skills. Records include correspondence, course materials, background information, membership records; and financial information.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was transferred from the University of Michigan Accounting Department (donor no. 2942 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Early in 1918 the federal government polled universities throughout the country in order to determine the schools' capacities to train members of the army in various technical skills. The University of Michigan responded that it could accommodate 200 soldiers, and in April 1918 a detachment of 200 Students' Army Training Corps was sent to Ann Arbor for a two month training program. In June 1919 the number of trainees in Ann Arbor was increased to 700, in August the number was 1,140, and at the beginning of the fall semester, 1919 the university was prepared to receive 2,800 men. At the program's peak, the university absorbed 3,600 army students, largely disrupting the normal academic functions of the school. Housing and feeding such a large number of soldiers proved extremely difficult and was never satisfactorily arranged. With the signing of the armistice which ended active hostilities, the SATC program was quickly disbanded.
The record group is arranged into four series: Correspondence and Other Documents; Course Work and other Bound Material; Membership Information; and Financial Records. Within the bound records, there is a volume relating to the history of the Corps. This volume also includes photographs depicting the training of students in auto mechanics, as telephone electricians, and in other technical courses and exercises.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; United States. Army. Students' Army Training Corps (University of Michigan); World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence and Other Documents
  - Undated, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - April-June 1918 (Box 1)
  - July 1918 (Box 1)
  - August 1918, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - September 1918, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - October 1918, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - November 1918, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - December 1918, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - January 1919, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - February-May 1919 (Box 1)
- Course Work and other Bound Material
  - Telephone Electricians (Volume 1) (Box 2)
  - Telephone Electricians (Volume 2) (Box 2)
  - Auto Mechanics (Box 2)
  - Machinists, Carpenters, Gunsmiths, Blacksmiths, etc. (Box 2)
  - Surveyors, Draftsmen (Box 2)
  - Pictorial Record, History, Administration (Box 2)
    (include photographs)
- Membership Information
  - Lists (Box 2)
  - List of students in various units and sections, 1918-1919, 1 volume (Volume 1)
    (also include lists of regular students and naval unit students)
- Financial
  - Budget ledger, 1918 (Volume 2)